[music]
[Instructor] So, we're using loops
to control
all of the spawning of our enemies,
but 1 of the things that we have to do,
is we need to make
it so when all of these enemies
fall off, you can see they still exist
in our scene. So we actually,
need to remove them,
and then we'll add in some functionality
to spawn new waves.
First what we're going to do
is in our Enemy Script,
we're going to remove the enemies
when they fall off the scene.
So we'll do that in our Update() method
so we can always check their position.
So, if the enemy's current position,
on the y < -10,
so if it falls below
Plane of our platform,
then we'll "Destroy()"
the current gameObject, cool.
So now, in our SpawnManager,
since we know that our
enemies will be destroyed
when they leave the platform,
we actually want to keep track
of the number of enemies that we have.
So, we're going to make
a public variable for now
so we can see the numbers of enemies
that are the screen.
We'll make it an int,
and then we'll just call it enemyCount
so we can keep track.
In our Update() method,
is actually where we're going to be
keeping the count of all of our enemies.
They will be deleted
at different points in time,
so we use enemyCount,
and we'll set this using a new method
to find all of the enemies
in the scene.
We use the
FindObjectsByType<>() method
to locate all objects in our scene
that have a specific script attached
to them as a component.
In this example,
we'll use the Enemy script
as all of our enemies will have
that script attached to them.
This is similar to using “GetComponent()”
where you specify the component name
inside the <> to identify those objects.
The “FindObjectsByType” method also
requires a parameter inside the parentheses,
which specifies the order in which the elements
should be stored after being found.
For our purposes,
the order is not relevant;
we only care about
how many objects are found.
Therefore, we can pass
“FindObjectsSortMode.None”
as the argument,
which ensures that the elements
won't be sorted after they are found.
And now, you can see
we have a problem here.
So, this is actually
a really useful part
of knowing the difference
between return and void now.
So actually, if we hover over,
you can see that first
word says it returns
an array of enemies,
and the problem
here is that it can't actually
set an array of enemies
to an integer.
You need an integer
to set an integer.
So actually, because this is an array,
we can actually use
the ".Length" method.
And so now .Length will
actually return the number
of enemy Objects in our scene.
So now that we can keep track
of all the different enemies,
we'll need to know when we should
spawn more enemies.
So, we'll use an if() statement
to track that condition,
so if the enemyCount()
ever becomes or,
using our comparison operator
here with the 2 equal signs, 0,
then we should spawn more enemies.
And just to see, and make sure it works,
I'll set this to 1 for now.
After all 3 of our enemies
fall off the scene,
our Enemy Count should hit 0,
and then it will spawn 1 more enemy.
So now in Unity,
if I select our Spawn Manager
in our Project Hierarchy you can see
that the current Enemy Count is 0.
When I Play our game,
you can see 3 enemies spawn,
I pick up the Powerup,
3 enemies fall off,
get set to 0,
and then it sets it back to 1
because it spawns a new enemy.
So, what you're going to do
is in your Enemy Script,
you're going to add
some lines of code
just to detect when an enemy
falls off the scene
to be destroyed,
in our Update() method.
In our SpawnManager Script,
you're going to create
a new variable.
We'll make it public
for now so we can see it change.
We'll make it an integer
called enemyCount.
In our Update() method,
we're going to set enemyCount
by finding objects of type,
and the type we're going to use is
actually the Enemy Script.
And then we need to get the Length
of what that returns
because it actually gives us
an array, and we just need a number.
Then we're going to create a new
if() statement, using the enemyCount.
And when enemyCount becomes 0,
then we'll spawn a new enemy wave...
with 1 enemy.
So, now it's your turn.
[music]